Guide to the George W. Fox Collection of American Indian Ledger Drawings and Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George W. Fox Collection of American Indian ledger drawings and photographs
1867-1885
WA MSS S-2893
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.1
(5 boxes)
Ledger drawings by American Indians and photographs collected by George W. Fox, 1867-circa 1885. Ledger drawings in the collection include two discrete disbound volumes created in 1876 by Wohaw, a Kiowa Indian, and Soaring Eagle, a Cheyenne Indian. Photographs include portraits of American Indians and views of Indian Territory by William Stinson Soule, as well as portraits of American Indian students and views by John Nicholas Choate related to the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. The collection also includes stereograph portraits of American Indian prisoners at Castillo de San Marcos (Fort Marion) in Saint Augustine, Florida, by photographers O. Pierre Havens and George Pierron. Other photographs include views of sites along the Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway in Texas by Peter Fassold and Samuel Burnett Hill, as well as other images of Texas and California by Charles Turner Collier and August R. Mignon.
Fox, George W., collector., 1853-1886
Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902
Collier, Charles Turner, 1853-
Fassold, Peter, approximately 1843-
Havens, O. Pierre, 1838-1912
Hill, Samuel B., 1840-1917
Mignon, August R., 1844-1915
Pierron, Geo. (George), 1816-
Soaring Eagle, approximately 1847-1886
Soule, William S. (William Stinson), 1836-1908
Wohaw, approximately 1853-1924
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana and Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2002.
Custodial History
Formerly owned by the Cumberland County Historical Society, Greenwich, New Jersey.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George W. Fox
George W. Fox (1853-1886) was born in Pennsylvania, the son of George W. Fox (1820-1888). He married Laura E. Shinn Fox Bowen (1858-1933) and they had two daughters, Laura M. Fox (later Mulford) (1878-1965) and Nana S. Fox (later Oliver) (1882-1942). Fox worked as a trader with John "Jack" S. Evans at Fort Sill, Indian Territory, and became an interpreter for Comanche Indians. From 1875 to March 1877, Fox worked with Richard Henry Pratt (1840-1924) and American Indian prisoners of war at Fort Marion (Castillo de San Marcos ) in Saint Augustine, Florida. Fox probably died in New Jersey. In 1890, his widow married Daniel Albert Bowen (1855-1912).
Scope and Contents
Ledger drawings by American Indians and photographs collected by George W. Fox, 1867-circa 1885. Ledger drawings in the collection include two discrete disbound volumes created in 1876 by Wohaw, a Kiowa Indian, and Soaring Eagle, a Cheyenne Indian. Photographs include portraits of American Indians and views of Indian Territory by William Stinson Soule, as well as portraits of American Indian students and views by John Nicholas Choate related to the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania. The collection also includes stereograph portraits of American Indian prisoners at Castillo de San Marcos (Fort Marion) in Saint Augustine, Florida, by photographers O. Pierre Havens and George Pierron. Other photographs include views of sites along the Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway in Texas by Peter Fassold and Samuel Burnett Hill, as well as other images of Texas and California by Charles Turner Collier and August R. Mignon.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Ledger Drawings by American Indians, 1876. II. Photographs, 1867-circa 1885.
Cheyenne Indians; Cheyenne Indians -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Kiowa Indians; Kiowa Indians -- Pictorial works; Indian art -- Great Plains; California -- Pictorial works; Carlisle (Pa.) -- Pictorial works; Florida -- Pictorial works; Indian Territory -- Pictorial works; Pennsylvania -- Pictorial works; Saint Augustine (Fla.) -- Pictorial works; Texas -- Pictorial works; Ledger drawings; Photographic prints; Choate, J. N. (John N.), 1848-1902; Collier, Charles Turner, 1853-; Fassold, Peter, approximately 1843-; Fox, George W., 1853-1886; Havens, O. Pierre, 1838-1912; Hill, Samuel B., 1840-1917; Mignon, August R., 1844-1915; Pierron, Geo. (George), 1816-; Pratt, Richard Henry, 1840-1924; Soaring Eagle, approximately 1847-1886; Soule, William S. (William Stinson), 1836-1908; Wohaw, approximately 1853-1924; Castillo de San Marcos (Saint Augustine, Fla.) -- Pictorial works; Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway Company -- Pictorial works; United States Indian School (Carlisle, Pa.) -- Pictorial works
- Ledger Drawings by American Indians, 1876; Series I; 0.42; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of ledger drawings by Wohaw, a Kiowa Indian, and Soaring Eagle, a Cheyenne Indian.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Ledger Drawings by Wohow and Ledger Drawings by Soaring Eagle.
  Biographical/Historical note
  Ledger drawings are representational drawings of scenes from the lives of nineteenth century Plains Indians, with an emphasis on martial accomplishments. Their name derives from the ruled ledger books in which the artists often executed the drawings, which were usually obtained from soldiers or traders.
  - Ledger Drawings by Wohaw
    Wohaw (1855-1924), also known as Wo-haw, Wohow, Beef, Gu-hau-de, or Wolf Robe, was a Kiowa Indian. In October 1874, the United States Army arrested him for participating in the the murder of Jacob Dilsey in 1873, as well as the murders of Manuel Ortega and Lucien Munos in 1874. In April 1875, authorities transferred him to Fort Marion in Saint Augustine, Florida. Following his release from Fort Marion in 1878, Wohaw returned to Indian Territory. He served in the Indian Police between 1879 and 1880, as well as a scout with Troop L of the 7th United States Cavalry from 1891 to 1895.
    Volume of ledger drawings by Wohaw disbound previous to acquisition.
    - Original boards, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      One board includes pencil and ink inscriptions that identify the creator of the volume as Wohow, September 1876
    - Five American Indians mounted on horses and hunting deer, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Two American Indians stalking deer, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Five American Indians stalking grazing buffalo, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A group of American Indians wearing civilian clothes and holding bows posing for a photographer while two European American couples look on, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A military camp scene showing United States soldiers and an American Indian woman, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fourteen American Indians shown from behind, listening to an American Indian woman addressing them, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Three American Indians hunting wild turkey, buffalo, and deer, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - A wigwam and the six American Indians from behind, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Nine American Indians hunting buffalo, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - United States Army officer addressing a large group, probably the American Indian prisoners wearing their United States Army standard issue dress, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Indians and European Americans interacting on the street; an European American male depicted talking to an American Indian, while a European American female addresses a bare-chested Indian. At the far right, an American Indian depicted riding in a carriage, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Five American Indians hunting buffalo; two of the American Indians use handguns, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - A group of European American men and wagons, surrounded by five wigwams, two mounted American Indians, and an additional American Indian hunting, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Nine men in a sailboat, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Drawings by Soaring Eagle
    Volume of ledger drawings by Soaring Eagle disbound previous to acquisition. Most of the sheets have drawings on their rectos and versos.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Originally given by Soaring Eagle to Laura E. Shinn Fox, October 5, 1876.
    Soaring Eagle (circa 1847-1886), also known as Sore-Eyed, Ma-ah-chis, Oh-u-oh, or Ouhoh, was a Cheyenne Indian. In December 1874, the United States Army arrested him for killing a buffalo hunter named George Brown near Fort Wallace, Kansas, and then transferred him to Fort Marion in Saint Augustine, Florida in April 1875. In April 1878, he began studying at the Hampton Institute, and then briefly attended the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania in June 1879. From June to October 1879, he assisted farmers in Lee, Massachusetts. In October 1879, he returned to the Cheyenne and Arapaho Agency.
    - Original boards, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      One board includes pencil sketches of figures by Soaring Eagle, as well as pencil and ink inscriptions that identify its provenance from Laura E. Shinn Fox Bowen to her grandchildren, Alberta G. Mulford Knettle (1904-2000) and Joseph Ralph Mulford, Jr. (1912-2001) of Bridgeton, New Jersey.
    - Verso: Blank, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Verso: Locomotive with conductor, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Verso: Sixteen American Indians, seated, receiving instructions from two European American women, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Verso: Large group of American Indians huddled on the observation deck of a lighthouse, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Verso: Locomotive pulling into a town, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Verso: Two American Indians, camouflaged by deer hides, hunting eight deer, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Verso: American Indian camp with four American Indians engaged in target practice with bow and arrow, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Verso: American Indian camp, with an United States flag flying above it, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Verso: Overhead landscape view, showing rivers, a village, and horses grazing, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Verso: Nineteen American Indians in battle with unseen enemy while eighteen additional American Indians hide in the brush, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Verso: American Indian camp showing two horses, six Indians, and a tipi, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Verso: Four American Indians hunting buffalo, one American Indian being trampled, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Verso: Two American Indians roping wild horses, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Verso: United States military fort, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Verso: Herd of buffalo, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Verso: Blank, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Verso: Blank, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Photographs, 1867-circa 1885; Series II; 0.63; (3 boxes)
  Series II is organized into five subseries: Photographs of American Indians and Indian Territory by William Stinson Soule; Photographs of Castillo de San Marcos (Fort Marion), Saint Augustine, Florida; Photographs by John Nicholas Choate related to the United States Indian School; Photographs of the Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway, Texas; and Photographs of Texas and California.
  Most photographs have ink stamps on their versos: "Pirate House Library, Cumberland County Historical Society, Greenwich, N.J. 08323"
  - Photographs of American Indians and Indian Territory by William Stinson Soule
    Organized under five headings: Studio Portraits, Exterior Portraits, Exterior Views, Interior Views, and Copy Photographs
    William Stinson Soule (1836-1908) was a photographer in Indian Territory. During the American Civil War, Soule enlisted in April 1861 as a private in the 13th Regiment Massachusetts Volunteer Infantry. He suffered wounds during the battle of Antietam, and was retained as a government clerk until his discharge in August 1864. After the war, he briefly operated a photograph gallery in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania. From around 1867 to 1874, Soule worked as a sutler to forts and villages in the Indian Territory, as well as a photographer of American Indians and soldiers in the region. In April 1875, Soule married Ella August Blackman (1854-1909), and they had two children, Lucia Augusta Soule (1877-1966) and Mary Eliza Soule (1882-1911). He operated businesses in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Saint Albans, Vermont, and eventually settled in Melrose, Massachusetts. In 1885, he bought the Soule Photographic Company from his brother John Payson Soule (1828-1893), which he operated until his retirement in 1900.
    Photographs of American Indians and sites in Indian Territory, 1867-1875.
    - Studio Portraits
      Arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual or first person listed in the portrait followed by unidentified individuals.
      - Studio portrait of Ba-e-tha and Hack-e-a, also known as Zah-e-cha and Har-ke-i, two Arapaho Indian women, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 34)
        Misidentified on recto of mount as Cheyenne Indians
      - Kicking Bird (circa 1835-1875), also known as Tene-angop'te, Ton-e-onca, Ton-ne-on-co, Eagle Who Strikes with his Talons, or Striking Eagle, a Kiowa Indian man wearing partial native dress, blanket with hair pipe breastplate and holding bow and arrows in fur quiver, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Lone Wolf the Elder (circa 1820–1879), also known as Gui-pah-gho or Guipago, a Kiowa Indian man wearing a blanket and ornaments and holding pipe-tomahawk, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 36)
        Ink stamp on verso: George W. Fox
      - Otter Belt, also known as Paatsoko Nehki, a Comanche Indian man wearing face paint and ornaments, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Satanta (circa 1820-1878), also known as Set-tain-te or White Bear, a Kiowa Indian man wearing partial native dress and a peace medal, Hudson Bay blanket, bow, arrows, and quiver, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Son of Pacer, an Apache Indian boy wearing partial native dress and with fur-wrapped braids, ornaments, hair pipe breastplate and pipe-tomahawk, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Ta-her-ye-qua-hip (died 1888), also known as Ter-ger-quoip or Horseback, a Comanche Indian man wearing partial native dress, wearing a blanket, neck scarf with metal gorget, and holding beaded pouches and animal skin quiver with bow, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 40)
        Ink inscription on verso: J. Ralph Mulford, Jr.
      - Ta-nun-co, also known as Standing Sweat House or Tape-day-ah, a Kiowa Indian man in native dress and with fur hat, pipe-tomahawk, fur bow case and fur quiver, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Tsen-tainte (died 1892), also known as White Horse, a Kiowa Indian man wearing a hair pipe breastplate, blanket, and ornaments, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Zepko-ette (1833-circa 1900), also known as Za-ko-yea or Big Bow, Kiowa Indian man with wrapped braid and wearing a peace medal, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Apache Indian man, possibly a nephew of Pacer, with fur-wrapped braids and wearing native dress and a blanket with quillwork, and hair pipe choker and breastplate and holding a bow and arrows, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Two Kiowa Indian women in native dress and with ornaments, 1867-1875 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Exterior Views
      Arranged alphabetically by American Indian camps, and then by the name of the principal individual, followed by images of unidentified camps, structures, and landscapes.
      - Camp of Iron Mountain, also known as Boo-e-yah-toyah, a Comanche Indian, showing tipis and individuals in blankets, 1867-1873 (Box 3, Folder 46)
        Image includes a self-portrait of William Stinson Soule wearing a buffalo robe with the group in native dress outside a tipi.
        Printed image number on recto: 3.
      - Camp of Lone Wolf, also known as Quir-par-ko, a Kiowa Indian, showing tipis, bundles on storage racks, and an individual in a blanket, 1867-1873 (Box 3, Folder 47)
        Printed image number on recto: 6.
      - Camp of Pacer, also known as Peso or Essa-queta, an Apache Indian, with Mount Scott in distance, near Fort Sill, Indian Territory, 1867-1873 (Box 3, Folder 48)
        Ink stamp on recto: George W. Fox
      - Camp of Ta-her-ye-qua-hip (died 1888), also known as Ter-ger-quoip or Horseback, a Comanche Indian, showing tipis and group four individuals in native dress outside a tipi, 1867-1873 (Box 3, Folder 49)
        Printed image number on recto: 2.
      - Comanche Indian camp with a trader's tent, 1870-1872 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Group of American Indians, European Americans, and soldiers in front of the store of John "Jack" S. Evans and Co. at Fort Sill, Indian Territory, 1869-1875 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Men at riverbank of Medicine Bluff Creek with a camp of tipis in background, 1875 February (Box 3, Folder 52)
        Trader John S. Evans is probably the man second from the left.
        Pencil mark on recto over an unidentified man.
      - Medicine Bluffs, near Fort Sill, Indian Territory, 1869-1870 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Mount Scott near Fort Sill, Indian Territory, includes a European American man posed sitting on a boulder and holding a rifle, 1867-1873 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Photographs of Castillo de San Marcos (Fort Marion), Saint Augustine, Florida
    Castillo de San Marcos is the oldest masonry fort in the continental United States. Located on the shore of Matanzas Bay in the city of Saint Augustine, Florida, the Spanish began its construction in 1672. In 1763, the British gained control of Florida and the fort, which became Fort Saint Mark; control of the fort returned to Spain in 1783. In 1821, the fort became United States Army base renamed Fort Marion, honoring Francis Marion (circa 1732-1795). Fort Marion chiefly served as a military prison to incarcerate members of various Native American tribes. In 1942, an act of the United States Congress restored the original name, Castillo de San Marcos.
    O. Pierre Havens (1838-1912) was born in New York, and moved to Savannah, Georgia, in 1872 and established a photography studio. In 1888, he relocated to Jacksonville, Florida, where he maintained a studio until his death.
    George Pierron (born 1816) was a photographer in Saint Augustine, Florida.
    - Havens, O. Pierre, Stereograph of a group of Cheyenne Indians in their native costume, confined in Fort Marion, Saint Augustine, Florida, circa 1875 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      Printed image number on verso: 114
    - Havens, O. Pierre, Stereograph of a group of Cheyenne and Arapaho Indians in native costume, confined in Fort Marion, Saint Augustine, Florida, circa 1875 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      Printed image number on verso: 121
    - Pierron, George, Stereograph of American Indian prisoners upon arrival at Fort Marion, Saint Augustine, Florida, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      Ink numbers on the recto of the stereograph correspond to a label affixed to its verso that identifies the individuals.
    - Unidentified photographer, Stereograph of Richard Henry Pratt (1840-1924) with five American Indian men and an European American man at Fort Marion, Saint Augustine, Florida, circa 1875-1878 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Unidentified photographer, American Indian men wearing uniforms and posed in formation and sitting on top of a building at Fort Marion, Saint Augustine, Florida, circa 1875 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Ink inscription on verso misidentifies the images as Fort Sill
  - Photographs by John Nicholas Choate related to the United States Indian School
    Organized under three headings: Studio Portraits, Exterior Portraits, Exterior Views, Interior Views, and Copy Photographs
    John Nicholas Choate (1848-1902) was a commercial photographer in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, as well as the unofficial photographer for the United States Indian School. From when the school opened in 1879, until his death, Choate photographed nearly every student upon arrival and during their school career, as well as school activities, staff, and visiting chiefs, dignitaries, and families.
    United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, was founded in 1879 by Richard Henry Pratt (1840-1924) under authority of the United States federal government. The school became the first federally funded off-reservation boarding school for American Indians. Pratt established the school based on the principle that American Indians were equal to European-Americans, and that native children immersed in mainstream American culture would learn skills to advance in society. The school closed in 1918.
    Photographs related to the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, 1879-1880.
    - Studio Portraits
      Arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual or first person listed in the portrait.
      - Studio portrait of David Blue Teeth, Nathan Standing Cloud, Marshall, son of Bad Milk; Pollock, son of Spotted Tail; and Hugh, son of Whirlwind Soldier; Dakota Indian boys from the Rosebud Agency wearing school uniforms, circa 1879 (Box 4, Folder 60)
        Letterpress label affixed to the verso of the print identifies the boys and their fathers.
      - Studio portrait of Gsai-au-tit-sa, also known as Mary Ealy; Jan-i-uk-tit-sa, also known as Jennie Hammaker; Leai-s-se-u-lu-ti-wa, also known as Frank Cushing; and Tas-we-ea-tas-lun-kia, also known as Taylor Ealy, in partial native dress as they arrived at the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, from the Zuni Pueblo, circa 1879 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - Studio portrait of Mary Roosevelt Hyde (1850-1910), matron and superintendent of the girls' department at the United States Indian School in Carlisle, Pennsylvania, with Nellie Carey (born circa 1863), an Apache Indian woman, and three Pueblo Indian girls, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - Studio portrait of Justine La Framboise and Nancy Renville, Dakota Indian girls, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 63)
        Ink inscription image number on verso: 4.
      - Studio portrait of Little Raven (circa 1810-1889), also known as Ho-hawk-a-she, Ho-sa, Hósa, Ochohisa, Ochohisa, Ohaste, or Young Crow, and his daughter, Anna Little Raven, Arapaho Indians, circa 1879 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - Studio portrait of five American Indian girls wearing school uniforms, identified as Lucy, a Cheyenne Indian, and Leah, an Arapaho Indian, as well as Fanny, Mabel, and Laura, Kiowa Indians, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 65)
        The girls are also identified elsewhere as Lucy, Ella Hippy, Fanny, Mabel, and Laura.
      - Studio portrait of Joseph Nonway and Moses Wishacoby, Menominee Indians, wearing school uniforms, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - Studio portrait of Red Shirt (1847-1925), also known as Ógle Lúta, Ogilasa, or Joseph Red Shirt, a Lakota Indian man, wearing partial native dress and with fur-wrapped braids and feather fan, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Studio portrait of Son of the Star (circa 1825-1881), also known as Rushing Bear, an Arikara Indian man, wearing native dress and with feather headdress, feather fan, pipe bag, scalp and peace medal, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 68)
        Ink inscription on verso misidentifies him as an Arapaho Indian.
      - Studio portrait of Spotted Tail (1823/1833-1881), also known as Sinte Gleska, Sinte-galeshka, Cin-te-gi-le-ska, or Tshin-tah-ge-las-kah, Lakota Indian, 1823-1881, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Studio portrait of Tso-de-ar-ko, also known as Trodearko, a Wichita Indian man; Benjamin H. Clark (1842-1914), a European American interpreter; and Wild Horse, also known as Kobi, White Horse, Tsen-T'ainte, a Comanche Indian man posed holding a paper fan; both American Indian men wearing blankets and ornaments and lived at the Kiowa and Comanche Agency, 1880 (Box 4, Folder 70)
        Ink inscription image number on verso: 17.